all right good morning everybody
and
let me check the schedule here
hey tim we go for 45 minutes right
that's correct
okay so
that means 7 13 i will stop
okay and then we'll take a break
all right welcome back to the angel
debates the devil
uh
if you know the story oh tim it's uh
it's uh alternating translation right
uh it's simultaneous so it's it's in
another translation channel so just take
your time give brass please i'll take
big breath
uh
so
as you heard about in the
announcement for this program
uh we started reading this i started
reading this with my teacher uh ken
rinpoche
about i don't know
it must have been about
uh 35 years ago
and
he said i want to teach you guys this
very unusual book you know and and i was
i was like well
you know
what's the book and he said well it's a
poem
and it was written about 350 years ago
uh
or you could say 400 375
and it was written by uh his holiness
the first pension law
whose name was los angeles
and
i love him very much he's an amazing
teacher
and i i taught about him for three years
uh
about 20 years ago at diamond mountain
and uh he's a great great poet
uh
he we translated
his poetry
secret poetry
and i translated a lot of it in
one of my students john stilwell who's a
bad boy
he published it without asking me
so
even though it's a secret poetry
probably you can find it somewhere
uh
and it's it's really beautiful poetry
uh about his secret practice
and then he wrote a great great
philosophy books
uh i love his explanation
of how your body uh turns into
living diamond
uh if you succeed in in this path and
i don't think you can find it anywhere
else
so it's written so clearly
and that's called the transformation of
the five
heaps of the five parts of body and mind
so
maybe someday we can go through that
together
uh
he also of course wrote a very famous
llama
uh which is called delam
which means a path to
this
or it can also mean easy paths to blizz
and that's uh you can find it at the
beginning
it's the first three
of the 18 courses
the advanced courses of aci
and
tim and me are we know we're talking
about uh
ways to
to teach those courses uh to more people
uh and we'll be talking more about that
so i thought today we could just go
through the the poem
uh i started uh
reading this poem 11 years ago
uh
i started translating it
and we had a program in phoenix arizona
uh there's a beautiful uh
arboretum there arboretum means a tree
garden public tree garden
and you know in arizona we don't have
any rain
so the
tree garden is mostly some cactus
but they are very beautiful
and the garden allowed us to have the
program there so i started this
teaching
11 years ago
and
when my teacher taught me this book we
had some obstacles
i'm hearing someone's microphone on with
a bunch of kids
uh
that's the obstacle well my teacher had
some obstacles to finish this book and
and actually
we never finished it together
and
then he passed away
i
try to finish it uh the whole thing
and translate it because it's so
beautiful
so
uh let me tell you a little bit about
the story
uh the angel in this case is our
understanding of the pen
but in his uh
book in his poetry
the angel i don't know i feel like she's
a very very beautiful
and wise
being
who is the good side of our mind
so in the
i don't know about your country but in
my country
when we're growing up
uh they will show us uh pictures like
you saw
on the announcement for this program
where there's an angel on one side of
your head
and there's a devil on
and i don't know my devil is always
trying to get me to eat donuts
and my angel is always trying to get me
to eat vegetables
and
they are fighting uh most of the day i i
don't know i'm always
thinking about it
the devil says oh wouldn't it be nice to
have a donut we didn't have a donut for
two weeks three weeks you know
i understand they're not so good for you
but
you know it's one of life's pleasures
and if you have one once in a while it's
probably okay
and then the angel will say no no
everything you eat uh becomes part of
you you are what you eat
and
every time you eat something unhealthy
it becomes part of
your body you know
yesterday
uh we were having a teaching uh
interesting teaching
we said well you are what you eat this
is a famous saying in english
because what you eat
your body becomes that
so actually my body today
is oh hang on i'm making a soup for my
wife hang on
uh we both got covered this week
and uh i recovered first
and she's still a little bit sick so i'm
cooking for her
okay
so
the devil will
try to get you to eat a donut
and the angel will say no no let's have
some vegetable you know
and then they will argue
inside of your mind
and that's what's happening in this poem
uh
except the angel is specifically
my understanding of the pen okay my
understanding and it's
every time i teach the pen
i i want to reach into the zoom call and
grab your neck and say come on
don't you get it
don't you understand
it's a proof it's a total proof you know
if everybody in the world
was logical if if we were completely
logical
then after i explained the pen to you
look
when i
when i hold this up
these pieces
i see a pin
and very very simple when i
show this to a dog
then
they want to chew it they don't see a
pin
and it sounds like a child's uh story
you know it sounds like a story that you
tell to your children
when you put them to bed maybe tim can
write a children's book called the pen
it sounds like a children's story but
it's not
it's a 100 percent proof if you if your
mind
really
pure and clean you can see it
it's a hundred percent proof already
that things are coming from us they are
not coming from their own side okay
and i know it sounds simple
and i read it a thousand times
uh
i know probably you're tired to hear
about the pin
but if you really understand it
then you know that you can change this
whole world
okay
and we have this word in
in the buddhist teaching called
mandala
and it means a perfect world
there's no war
there's no sickness
uh there's no death
there's no sadness
and it is if the pen is possible if the
pen is true
then then the mandala is possible then
it is possible
to change this world
and you heard about places like
amitabha's paradise you know
and um
heaven
you know and and
[Music]
can we go is there really such a thing
you know
i heard some
foolish people told me
well gesla uh
heaven would be boring you know
and always the same thing
no fun
and then some foolish people said
heaven cannot exist
because we only know good things when we
see bad things
and and i even heard some people
explain uh this is what dependent
origination means
uh only because of bad things
uh we can see good things and that's
completely
totally
wrong
and
like i hate it's just stupid
okay
that's like saying you can't have an
apple unless you have a
banana
you know
it's not true you can eat apple it
tastes great
even you don't have a banana
so
it is possible
to
if the pan comes from me
and then i can make a perfect world and
we should do it right there's a places
like amitabha's paradise
those guys already finished they had
these classes a long time ago
by the way they had the same class okay
they are not so different from us we are
all the same
and those uh
buddhas police officers enlightened
beings
they started out just like us they're
not different from us in the beginning
i always think uh we are the
student in the back of the class we are
the little bit slow student in the back
of the class and the students in the
front of the class you know in america
that wants to raise their hand right
away i know i know
that's like
siddhartha maitreya
you know my juicer those guys already
graduated
you know
and uh
we are kind of the slow kids in the
class because
but our world we can catch up okay and
this kind of teaching
uh will help us to catch up we will
catch up
okay and and you and me we will live in
a perfect world
uh i've seen those worlds and and then
you can
teach other people uh and it would be
fun it'll to
to do it together is fun
and
i love this format about the angel
talking in your mind
and the devil talking in the other side
because the whole day
you and me are like that you know we
have angel talking on one side
we have devil talking on the other side
all day long
you know
uh
in in in the ancient books i'll be
dharma
they say that
uh it is possible to read other people's
minds
and if you meditate well you can you can
learn to do it
if your prana is flowing well if you do
your yoga for example ysi
then uh you can learn to read other
people's minds
but it's not so fun okay
you think it would be fun but it's not
very fun
it's kind of sad you know
the argument inside of everybody's mind
uh
the the very
turmoil all of this uh thoughts inside
of people's minds if you could really
read other people's mind
it wouldn't be very fun
because
all of us we have an angel and devil
arguing
in the mind all day you know
so let's uh start into this book this is
the 15th time i've thought it
uh tim and i checked ahead
i think we have
about three more
sessions so three more times in the next
i don't know two years
uh we should
we should read this together
and then we can finish it and we can
[Music]
publish it uh diamond cutter press
benefit
rosa those guys can publish this book
i think it's going to need a commentary
because it's a difficult book
i forgot to say one more thing about
this author
the story i like the most about him
is that
he was
doing a retreat in a cave
and uh
he you know if you ever do a long
retreat uh
you know that people have to cook for
you you're not supposed to
spend time cooking or buying groceries
you cannot go outside
so he had a guy doing his groceries
like every retreat person
and the guy left the note you know
usually they will communicate with notes
you know
they don't they try not to talk
and the grocery shopper came to the cave
and he left a note and he said uh bad
news
you're gonna have to move here retreat
you cannot finish in this cave
and uh
pension llama wrote back why
and the grocery shopper said uh
there's gonna be a war
uh in this valley
below the cave you know there's a war
happening
tomorrow
there's two armies coming here
two generals are leading two armies here
and there will be fighting a lot of
fighting a lot of people will die
and you shouldn't be here we you
shouldn't be in this cave you know
dinner
i guess that you can imagine
the first pension llama he's kind of
like
us you know he's like wow
that's pretty scary i i should run
tonight you know tonight i should
pack up my
meditation cushion and
i should run you know i should run to
another mom
i think we will do the same thing we
will think the same thing
then he couldn't sleep
and he started thinking more and more
wow if the people fight tomorrow
in this valley many many people will die
and
that's not that's not good you know i
should do something
and uh i love
that he
in the morning he broke his retreat
and he wrote a note to his uh
grocery shopper
he was already a pretty famous lumber
and he said tomorrow
i said you know
later in the day
bring me two bags of gold you know bring
me some gold coins
you know
and let's try to stop this war
and uh
when the armies were starting to
come together to fight
he ran out of his cave and he ran down
to the battlefield
and he stood between the two armies and
he said he was already famous teacher
he said if you want to kill each other
then you have to kill me first
i'm not moving you know and so the
army's had a lot of confusion
both armies respect him
and then he said let the two generals
come here
and let's have a conversation
[Music]
so
the two generals came out to the
battlefield
and
he said let's sit down let's sit down
you know and they said
he
said i have a suggestion
about this war
and the two generals said what's your
suggestion
and he said you know i'm a pretty famous
llama already and actually i have people
are always offering me money gold
i i have here two big bags of gold
gold coins
and
my suggestion is i give one bag to this
general
and i will give one back to this general
and then why don't you guys just go home
and relax and don't have war you know
and uh
that two generals who were
very happy to take the bag of gold
and they went home
and everybody lived happy
it's so simple how to solve the war
right
so i loved i love him he's so brave
and he's so smart and he's such a
beautiful
thinker
so i'm going to read uh
let's go through his verses okay i don't
know how far we can go grandpa
always tells stories and he doesn't
teach very fast
uh tim i think in
we're gonna try to have kind of short
sessions
and have question and answer
uh but do two two sessions this morning
uh my time
so in about 20 minutes
uh we will take up
we will take question and answer okay
tim is that good is that right
that sounds good
okay and then we'll take a little uh
break i can finish veronica's soup
making her soup
and then we'll have another class okay
here we go
by the way i wanted to uh
use this teaching
to invite all of my friends in the
sedona arizona
area
to come together
and it's it's really fun when we come
together for teaching at our college
in sedona but uh
i i think i still may have a i still may
be contagious from the coconut i had it
last this week
and i feel great i finished everything
but uh
i want i don't want to spread it to
other people so
we're gonna
do these two days at home and i'm sorry
for that but
when it's safe we can all sit together
in college okay
here we go verse 241
benjamin three in denver dude
okay
and let's go through the pieces
so
in buddhism we say that when you die if
you have been very generous
with your money
and if you share
what's the first perfection
some people say charity
some people say giving
i like this sharing okay if you really
like to share
your money your time
your wisdom
with other people
then after you die you will be born
as a devil
and deva means uh
i don't know when you see those uh
iron man
superman
uh
fantastic for
they are for
those guys all look like dimmer okay and
i think
those movies are made by people
who are remembering
their past life so i i think those
people who make those movies
they are a little bit remembering
their past life
so if we plant
great scenes
by sharing everything we have
with other people
then after we die we can go to this
temporary heaven
and uh of course we think it's a little
bit dangerous because even those people
die after a while
and they use up all their good karma
uh so it's we think it's not a very good
place to go
okay light said panzer so
do number
so when we see those movies you know we
can't meet
devas directly you and me
we don't have the power
we can watch a movie but on netflix
but we can't actually meet those real
people but they exist
[Music]
if you could
meet them
it feels to to us like their powers
are like the pen it feels like the
powers that they have to fly in the sky
or to fight with the very
bad guys
those powers are coming
from their side like the pen
they need thomas
[Music]
and
for a whole life
and for countless lifetimes before by
the way if you're alive now
if you're listening to me right now
then you had a past life come on okay
if if something can happen once
it can happen twice okay
that's why if your computer is not
working or
if your car's not doing sounding strange
you should get it fixed
right away
it doesn't get better
okay
uh if if if your car is making funny
noise
if your phone or your computer's doing
something
and you have to get it fixed now
because if a problem happens one time
it can happen two times or a thousand
times okay
so don't be lazy okay if you can be
alive now
if you can be born here
one time
come on don't be stupid you know if your
car can
can
give you trouble on monday
then of course it's going to give you
trouble
after tuesday
for sure
if you came to this world once
then it can happen again if it happened
twice
then it can happen a billion times okay
because time is endless
[Music]
so when we see this
when we read a story
from a teacher that we believe
that there are special people
they were very generous they shared
everything they had
and then after they died
uh those seeds created
uh
deva realm they are they are like um
animal superhero
okay
but then he says
if this deva is the way they seem if the
devil
is coming from the
like the pen is coming from the pen
then how can they die
and how can they finish that davos life
and how can they go someplace else okay
if
if this pen
is coming from its own side
it cannot run out of impossible
okay if the pen
is coming from its own side
it cannot run out of ink it's not
possible okay
uh
if a person
is coming from their own side
then they cannot die and they cannot
change
okay that's what the angel says all
right
so
i like this today's class tomorrow's
class because
uh
sometimes the angel doesn't talk much i
think she's shy angel
maybe a lot of angels are shy
and uh but uh she doesn't talk very much
in this section
she says look you know
if a pen is coming from the pen
and if the person is coming from the
person
then how can they die
uh she don't say po po means you heard
of pola
and poa means
how can they die and go to their next
birth so this whole
poetry
that we talk about today and tomorrow
they're going to discuss
how does it happen
when we die you know what happens to us
and
it's a very strange thing you know
when i went to i went to princeton
university supposed to be one of the
greatest universities in the world and i
think it is
uh
and i i spent four or five years there
nobody there's no class there
how to
die it's very funny you know there's in
the whole university
their endowment is 36 billion dollars
they have 36 billion dollars every year
to play with
and
there's no class about how to die
you know
it's amazing because everybody has to
die
it's like building the whole university
without a bathroom
you know
you know sooner or later you have to go
to the toilet you know it's it's very
stupid
to build a big university that doesn't
have a bathroom
what you couldn't think ahead for for
two hours or two hours
that you're gonna try you're gonna need
a bathroom
don't be stupid when you build a
university
and by the way we're building a new one
in japan
uh
when you're building a mercenary
[Music]
you should put some toilets there
think ahead
and
if you're teaching people about
life
then you should teach them about them or
you're or you are not a complete
university
okay
all right
so the angel says look
if if you come from your own side how do
you die how can you die
and what happens to you poor when you
when you go to your next life what
happens to you
and we should ask the question
you know we should be interested about
that you know
if somebody say uh
look pack your bag you know get get your
suitcase ready okay it's ready
where am i going
i don't know don't worry you're going
somewhere
you know and when where am i going
in the next few years okay don't worry
about it but pack your suitcase get
ready
then if if you don't ask where you're
going
if you don't ask where i'm supposed to
go why i have to pack a suitcase you got
to be crazy
you must be crazy
[Music]
this life uh sure this life finishes
yesterday i was 25 today i'm 69 i can't
believe it i'm like sharp you know
and
my hair also very air-conditioned though
and uh
i'm like shocked uh and it will happen
to everybody you should get ready
you know you should get ready you're not
gonna stay here someone's gonna take you
somewhere
okay
uh how
how can i
what can i do at that time okay
let's go to verse 242.
she don't say paul
[Music]
he said look you know everybody dies
and everybody goes somewhere after they
die why because you came here from
somewhere duh
okay don't be so stupid okay
no no when i die i just disappeared
well look last time you disappeared you
came back okay
you are here
so don't don't be foolish of course
you're gonna go somewhere
uh you came here
if something could happen once it can
happen twice
anybody can see that you know
okay anybody should fix their car right
away first time it makes a strange thing
uh
so
the the devil says no no people do die
uh people go on
you know
and then the angel says no no you said
the pen exists from its own side
so
you cannot die
if the pen exists from its own sign
then you also exist from your own side
if you exist from your own side
then you can't change
there's no reason you should change
okay and that's a difficult idea okay
if the pen
comes from its own side like we think
then it should not change it should it
should never run out of ink okay
if the ink
is in the pen
then it should never run out of me
we have to prove that okay it doesn't
make sense right away it doesn't make
sense i know it doesn't make sense
geshe-la
i just said the pen come from the
factory
people made it from oil
you know i bought it in the store
i didn't say the pen cannot change of
course it would change
that's why we have to go back to the
store and buy another one you know like
like that okay
then gestures say to you look
if the pen came from the store
if the pen was made in the factory
then it cannot change it cannot change
and it should never run out of ink yes
la
i never said that
of course a pen is made in a
when you write things the ink comes out
of the pen it goes on the paper
then that pen runs out of ink then you
have to buy another one
[Music]
i i didn't say the pen couldn't change
yeah but you're thinking that because
you're not asking where the pen came
from you're not asking okay you you are
not asking
why did the pen come to me okay
and this is a
big big important thing
if you want to have a happy life
and a successful duh
okay
that's a strange word right
if you want to have a happy life
and a successful death
then you have to ask
where did you come from okay
not
how you came to this world
but why you came to this world okay
if you tell me how the pen came to the
store
oh look questions made in japan
they sent the oil from
middle east to japan
on the ship
the factory got the oil the factory made
a pen
this is this is where the pen come from
gesla
but i say no
i you're telling me
how the pen came to me
you're not telling me why
okay
uh you have to try to understand the
difference okay how the pen came to me
oh they made it a factory they sent it
on a ship to america you you got the
penguin you bought it
no no that i understand that's how
the pen came to me but why me
why me and why this pen to me
you know oh gesh like come on they make
thousands of pens every day
some question has no answer
you know
that's why you lost your hair gifsla you
worry
about this
these funny questions you know
why this pain came to me don't worry
about it
just use it
but if you're a smart person you should
you should ask why your car broke today
why are your cars making strange sounds
why are your computers acting funny
you know not how
not how oh i know
when i turn on the car and i go for a
few miles it starts to make a sound
that's how
the question is
why my car
okay
tim's car didn't break
stanley's new car didn't break sage's
beautiful new car
didn't break
why my car okay
so
i say if you're a smart person
world
you gotta ask why me you see not how how
is easy
oh your your engine broke uh the
carburetor is dirty
that's why your cars are making noise
that don't tell me how
tell me why why my car
got carburetor problem
and tim's car did it
and
and sage's car didn't you know
come on you gotta ask these questions
okay
uh
it's important it's more important than
what i don't know what else you're
planning to do today
i have to go to the college film some
more things then i have to
take
finish the soup for my wife and stuff
like that
yeah
you think ahead how you're going to use
this day
but but the day that you have to take a
trip
to die and go somewhere
that's for sure going to happen you know
i don't know if i can get to the college
today
i don't know if the soup will burn or
not
[Music]
but i know i have to die i know that
that's for sure okay so
man we should get ready
and we have to ask
why we die
and not how we die okay
and that's uh that's what we're gonna do
in that next class
all right uncle tim are you gonna ask
ask the questions or i think we're going
to do 15 minutes of questions right am i
right
yeah it's early on but i think we have a
couple questions that came in
okay is this the schedule that we were
gonna do questions yeah we're gonna do
questions after 45 minutes
okay and then uh
we do 15 minutes of questions and take a
little uh soup making break or something
like that yep
okay
all right
um okay go ahead any question you like
let me turn my sharing off okay all
right
hey tim yes
why why bald people like zoom
because it cuts off the top of your head
yeah you see you can you can sit like
this
[Laughter]
okay
all right first question geshlife
by
by understanding this pen story we know
that
everything comes for us
and it's fair that
we can apply this to everyone even
children
but how do we think about this for say
victims of
domestic violence
people who are in deep sorrow or deep
depression
when they when we teach the pen story
and they're suffering so much
yeah that's a great question you know
so
you guys know uh i lived in a
mongolian monastery
for 25 years in near new york but the
whole town is mongolian town
and they are buddhist and they there
were about 15 monks there
old old mongolian monks and i studied
there i lived there for 25 years
with my teacher
and you know i i came from princeton
i was supposed to be a christian priest
i was accepted uh to the
college after princeton to be a
christian priest
uh so i was very active in the church
and and princeton has a beautiful
beautiful
cathedral it's very similar to the notre
dame
in paris it it they stole the plants
from from the amherst it's very
beautiful
and the music is very beautiful
and
it's a quiet beautiful place you know
very expensive maybe a billion dollars i
don't know
then uh
then i went to the small
from princeton directly i went to the
small
mongolian temple
and there were many uh beautiful statues
there buddha statue tara statue
maitreya statue
but there were also some terrible
terrible paintings you know like hell
paintings of hell
and
and the music was unbelievable
[Music]
and uh i couldn't meditate i couldn't it
sounded like world war ii you know
and
i said to my teacher you know how can
you
how can you have these terrible
paintings of hell and
and the music here is so loud how can
you meditate in
and he said look each culture has its
own
way you know in in mongolia this is
this is like a beautiful church you know
this is their custom it's different
it's different from your princeton
custom but it's beautiful
it's okay you know
then
on the
throne there's a teacher's throne
and there's a swastika
there's a nazi germany
swastika these are the nazi who killed
six million people
who who started a war that killed 130
million people
okay so
there's this swastika but actually this
sign come from uh india ancient india
and it's a very beautiful
uh it means a long life
swastika
means long life
and we always put them on the teacher's
chair
for 2 000 years before
hitler before nazis you know
and he explained everything to me i said
okay okay that that makes sense
maybe hitler took that sign
then one day uh jewish people came to
the
temple
can we see the
then i thought oh my gosh uh
this is going to be a problem
so i i
it was my job because i'm the youngest
monk i am the terrorist guide i am the
tour guide
so i have to walk around the temple with
them and explain everything
and
before they came
my teacher said you know what uh
hide the
hide the swastika
take it off
you know put it under the chair
don't show them
and i said why and and he said they
won't
understand that they will think we are
nazi or something they will think we are
bad people
so just hide it you know don't don't
show them
i said no it's okay i can explain it to
them he said no no something's
it's too early to explain to people you
know they're not ready
they saw this symbol their whole life
they
even they listen to you they they won't
really
feel comfortable in our in our temple
so i want you to hide it you know and i
and i did
and we had a good time and and they were
happy and then they
then we put the swastika back on on the
throne okay
uh
why am i saying that
in buddhism
we
understand
there's a time
when the student is not ready
that we shouldn't talk about some things
the student is not ready okay and
i believe
uh
why children die
in the in the car accident covered in
fire
small children you know
why
people so many people get abused when
they're kids sexually
or other kinds of abuse physical abuse
you know beating then
why
why it happens you know what's what's
the reason
and there should be a reason okay
everything has a cause
there is nothing
in the universe
that doesn't have a cause everything has
a cause everything has a why
and not just a heart don't tell me how
the kid was abused oh
they they went
someplace and some bad man caught them
they got abused that's how
you're telling me how
but tell me why why this child and why
not this child
you know and in buddhism
we do have answers to those questions
and
that's why we're all here that's why we
are listening to this class today
we we feel like we can find out the real
answer
but
there's a time when people are not ready
for the answer
[Music]
there's a time when we should just show
them
compassion
and show them love
and show them
emotional connection
even buddha
didn't always uh answer directly
if he thought the student is not ready
okay so there is a reason
why children die in in car accidents
when they are two years old in the fire
there is a reason why
some children are abused and some
children are not abused of course
there's a reason
uh but
but there's mostly
in our
tradition
the great teachers who say
maybe the students not ready to hear
about that okay maybe the student's not
ready
this thing is a hug
or maybe the student needs some love and
you can explain
later when they understand more
you can explain about past lives
you can explain about seeds
you can explain why everything has a
cause
but you have to choose the right time
and and when the parents are suffering
uh
it's not the right time
you have to
hide the
swastika
and it's time to give them a good hug
and
make them some zoom
and uh
and make them feel better but of course
everything has a reason
everything has a cost okay
and that's
i i met some psychiatrists recently that
they said uh
oh
why children have trouble
in the womb uh the mother ate a pizza
with too much uh
with too much uh hot sauce you know
and that's why the the child is uh
unhappy you know
because they don't understand there
should be a time before them
you know so they have to say this funny
thing like oh
uh this child
their whole life uh their mind was a
little bit uh
crazy
because a mom ate pizza
when she was pregnant and she ate the
wrong sauce you know or something like
that
and of course that's
it doesn't make sense okay
and
so
i think that
buddha
always checked the student first
and my teacher i believe was a buddha
and he taught me
uh hide the swastika you know like you
don't have to tell everything
the first day you know just
help the student uh at their own level
and then later you can
teach them
more about why everything has a cause
okay tim
you got another question
i do geshlo um in the beginning you told
us a a beautiful story about how the
first punch and lama
uh worked to stop a war
um and the couple questions have come in
that some people are experiencing more
in their own areas or the potential of
war
and they want to know that you know
based on that story as inspiration and
other
and other seeds what can we do to help
alleviate and reduce and not even
experience war
yeah that's a great question um
so when i was uh
you guys know this story i was a student
at princeton
it was during vietnam war
and
i was very disturbed by the war
and uh
i fought against that war
and uh i i even went to jail
for a short time
uh because i was uh trying to close uh
me and my friends tried to close a
weapons factory in this in the town of
princeton
and we did a peaceful we peacefully uh
sat in front of the door and we didn't
allow the workers to come in to make the
bombs
and
then the police arrested us and
uh
so i went to jail for a little bit and
i never forget that i went to a meeting
of the students
and
we're all trying to stop the war
and uh
there was a
thousand students in the meeting and uh
somebody said let's bomb the university
headquarte you know the office
let's bomb the president's office you
know
we'll we'll show them we can stop them
you know
and i got shocked you know i and then i
raised my hand there's a thousand
students there i said no and
i don't understand
it seems like you're doing the same
thing you know they are bombing
vietnam
and now
to fix it
you want to bomb the school i i it seems
like the same thing to me
i was very disturbed you know and
then later i got discouraged i thought
wow
you know i worked for
four or five years
constantly to stop the war
and it didn't really help much you know
i i i felt like
one person cannot do much you know i i'm
i'm
10 000 miles away from vietnam
and
i i don't know how i can stop the war
you know
so i got discouraged and uh
i didn't uh
do much after that
then after i studied uh emptiness
with my teacher
and i studied how karma how the seeds
open environmental results environmental
results
so my environment
my world
is coming from me just like the pin my
where
there's a conflict or there's could be
very serious conflict
uh
that's all coming from me you know and
and when i now i listen to the news i
was listening to the news last night
about this problem
uh when i was driving home from the
classes
and i
and you have to think oh this is coming
from me okay this problem
is coming from me
and
because it's coming from me
i can help stop it okay so you are never
helpless
if the pain is correct
then you are never helpless okay you can
always help
everybody in the world
can help to stop this this conflict
everybody can help we can all help
yes
i'm just one person
it's thousands of miles away but what
can i do
you know but
but it's still like the pin okay this
tensions
very very serious situation
uh for everybody for the whole world
that's coming from each one of us okay
each one of us
has planted the seeds
uh for this tension and we are seeing it
in our world
uh because it's coming from us and
because it's coming from me
one person
i can do something you know i don't have
to blow up the school
i don't have to go to jail
you know
uh i can help this situation
how
it's very very simple
so we are seeing
people not talking to each other
uh they are being actually they are
being selfish each each side is
is not thinking about the other side
what they need what they want
that's all because
i planted seeds like that i'm
a whole day
i'm taking care of myself
and i'm not taking care of other people
there are so many
millions of people
who don't have food today
millions
and uh i have too much food
you know
so
i i can stop the world i can do
something
if i just try to stop some
small seeds in my life like maybe i'm
having an argument with somebody in my
life
maybe there is someone
in my life
who feels threatened by me
you know i don't want to hurt other
people
but maybe there are some people who need
my
love
they need my attention
they need me to
comfort them
and
and so if i just
reach out to some people who are having
trouble in my own life
especially people who feel threatened by
me
uh then i'm i'm cancelling the seeds to
see the bigger tension okay so every
person on this call
you do have power to stop this conflict
you do you can do something
uh because it's coming from your seeds
so
it's very exciting you know today
call somebody
that you're having little trouble with
or comfort somebody who's not feeling
who's feeling that you are trying to
hurt them
and try to make it clear to them that
you love them
and that will change the seeds to see
the bigger conflict okay
and and when we come back to the text
we'll see
that even
how your future life goes
what kind of tension is there in the
future life
you can fix it now you can fix it in
this life okay if you can
change a whole world
then it's easy to change a small tension
okay
all right grandpa's gotta go check the
soups tim